[The Age of Awakening]
[觉醒年代]
[Episode Twenty-nine]
[第二十九集]
Brother Zhongfu, think about it
仲甫兄 你想想
Without the alarm clock
要是没有闹钟
Day and night, with all my heart and soul.
夜以继日 心沥血地晞鸣
The night follows the eyes, and the heart drips coffee and hoofs sound.
夜以继目， 心沥咖地蹄鸣
There will be no bomb.
便不会有炸弹的诞生
Although the bomb is powerful
炸弹的威力虽大
But it can't overcome people's inertia after all.
但是它终究战胜不了人之惰性啊
Only the alarm clock is needed.
只有需要闹钟
Constantly reminding and persisting.
持续不断地提醒着坚持着
To finally wake everyone up.
才能最终将所有人唤醒啊
Two gentlemen
二位先生
新港他
心刚他
He's dying.
他不行了
Take us there quickly.
快带我们去
Xingang
心刚
sir
先生
Sir is here.
先生来了
Don't move.
别动
It's okay. I can
没事我可以
I'm fine
我没事
Two gentlemen
二位先生
I want to say goodbye to you forever.
我要和你们永别了
Xingang, the biggest koo in my life
心刚此生最大的辜
I just met two gentlemen.
就是认识了二位先生
Unfortunately, the country is endangered.
可惜国家濒危
But the authorities fought the rabbit with the lion's strength.
当局却以狮子搏兔之力
Play against our patriotism.
弹压我等爱国之心
It makes me feel that in my own country.
让我感觉到在自己的国家
Be bullied as much as Japan.
和在日本一样地受欺负
What hope is there for such a country
这样的国家还有什么希望
Two gentlemen
二位先生
You have to save this country.
你们要救救这个国家
Save this nation.
救救这个民族
sir
先生
Do you remember
还记得吗
At the beginning we
当初我们
First meeting
第一次见面
I vomited a mouthful of phlegm on you.
我还吐了您一口痰
This is my bad temper.
我就是这个坏脾气
Xingang
心刚
You are a hero of the country.
你是国家的英雄
You are this country.
你是这个国家
Example of youth
青年的榜样
orchid
兰
I'm sorry
对不起
I can't take care of you anymore.
我以后不能再照顾你了
After I die.
我死之后
You're going to put my ashes
你要把我的骨灰
Take it back to my hometown in Jiaozhou Bay, Qingdao.
带回青岛胶州湾老家
Buried with my father.
和我的父亲埋在一起
When China takes back Qingdao.
等中国收回青岛的那一天
You're going to my grave
你要去我的坟前
Tell me and my father
告诉我和我的父亲
orchid
兰
Stop crying.
不哭了
I feel my hair has turned black.
我感觉我的头发都变黑了
yes or no
是不是
Haiwei
海威
Shiyan
世炎
Zhongxia
中夏
Look
你们看
It's black.
是黑了
Hei
黑了
Guo
老郭
Xingang
心刚
Wake up, Guo
你醒醒老郭
Xingang, wake up
心刚 你醒醒
Guo
老郭
Xingang
心刚
Guo, wake up
老郭 你醒醒
Guo Xingang
郭心刚
史鸷吾弟
适之吾弟
A few days above Shanghai
沪上方几日
Jingshi has been a thousand years old.
京师已千年
In the past few days since you left Beijing
你离京的这几日里
He Peking University
北京和北大
Great changes have taken place.
发生了天翻地覆的变化
May 4
五月四日
Destined to be one of the greatest
注定要成为中国历史上的
An important milestone.
一个重要的里程碑
Thirteen schools, mainly Peking University.
以北大为主的十三所学校
More than three thousand students marched in the streets.
三千余学子上街游行
Request to refuse to sign the Paris Peace Treaty
要求拒签巴黎和约
Severely punish traitors
严惩卖国贼
Defend China's sovereignty.
捍卫我中华主权
This shocked China and the whole world.
此举震惊了中国和整个世界
The reactionaries sent a large number of military police.
反动派派出了大批军警
And arrested 32 students.
打并逮捕了三十二名学生
Arouse strong opposition from the whole society
引起全社会强烈反对
All classes are taking action.
各个阶层都行动起来了
To the 7th.
到七日
The reactionary government had to release the arrested students.
反动政府不得不释放了被捕学生
The struggle won a staged victory.
斗争取得了阶段性的胜利
of course
当然
This also requires sacrifice.
这也需要牺特
My student Guo Xingang died today.
我的学生郭心刚今天牲了
Please tell Yannian this news.
请你把这个消息告诉延年
They are good friends.
他们是好朋友
I don't know if Secretary Ji's presence is far from welcome.
不知季司长大驾光 有失远迎
I'm going to find President Cai.
我这就去找蔡校长过来
No, no, no
不不不
Don't disturb principal Cai.
不必惊动蔡校长
You two go ahead and get busy.
你们两个先去忙吧
Headquarters order
本部令
Transfer bail students to court for trial
将保释学生移交法庭审讯
Make Peking University immediately rectify the style of study.
令北京大学即刻整饶学风
Director Li
李司长
You should give it to President Cai in person.
这您应该当面交给蔡校长才对
You also know
您也知道
I am just an errand boy.
我就是个跑腿的
Have no right to accept such orders!
根本无权接受这种命令啊
Hold
拿着
That's just for show.
这也就是做做样子嘛
There are three orders in this order.
本命令一共有三条
The first is to investigate Cai Yuanpei, president of Peking University.
第一条就是查办北大校长蔡元培
This one was crossed out by Chief Fu privately.
这一条被傅总长私自给划掉了
So say this command
所以说这个命令
It can never be handed over to Cai Yuanpei.
是绝不能交给蔡元培的
Understand?
明白吧
Brother Feng is promoted to a high position.
丰载兄高升高就
So that we can come to this first-class Qingyin class.
咱们才能来这一等清吟小班
Congratulations
恭喜恭喜
Recommended by Director Wu
蒙吴总监举荐
My brother is now "Gazette"
哥哥我现在是 《公言报》
Editor-in-Chief of Xuehai Chunqiu
《学海春秋》 栏目的主编
This is my public identity.
这是我的公开身份
My other identity is
我的另一个身份是
Senior detective compiled by Beijing Metropolitan Police Department.
京师警察厅在编的高级警探
It was also personally led by Director Wu Bingxiang.
也是吴炳湘总监亲自领导的
Deputy leader of the second intelligence group
第二情报组的副组长
My job is to collect
我的职责就是专门收集
Dynamic information of Beijing academic circles
北京学界的动态情报
Track and disrupt the student movement.
跟踪并瓦解学生运动
from this day onwards
从今天起
This Lanxiangban
这个兰香班
It is a point where we meet.
就是咱们接头的一个点
All of you.
你们所有人
They are all my informants.
都是我的线人
However, Brother Fengzai
不过丰载兄
But I heard that this "Gazette" one
我可听说这 《公言报》的
Xuehai Chunqiu
《学海春秋》
That's to support the student movement.
那可是专门支持学生运动
The government went against it.
跟政府对着干的呀
this
这
I'm afraid it's not consistent with our behavior.
这怕和咱的行为有些不符吧
That's a good question
这个问题问得好
dual identity
双重身份
This is the characteristic of our intelligence work.
这就是我们情报工作的特点
Only when you go deep into the tiger's den can you get a miraculous effect.
只有深入虎穴才能收到奇效
In the future, as informants of the metropolitan police department.
今后你们作为京师警察厅的线人
You should also learn to hide your identity.
也要学会掩饰好自己的身份
By the way, everybody.
对了 各位
Informants don't make money for nothing.
线人不白当 有钱赚啊
As long as you guys are diligent enough
只要你们几个够勤快
Guiwan nawu
桂金弯那屋
It will be our home in the future.
以后就是咱的家
Zhanggongzi
张公子
Hurry up
赶紧的
The dishes are all cold.
菜都凉了
Sister Liu
六姐
Girl, are you ready
姑娘准备好了吗
Walk
走着
classmates
同学们
Everybody gather around.
大家集合一下
Come and have a look.
都来看一看啊
classmates
同学们
Has everyone heard?
大家都听说了吗
President Cai Yuanpei Cai
蔡元培蔡校长
Sell our Peking University.
把我们北大给出卖了
Mr. Cai
蔡先生
impossible
不可能
Mr Cai, how is it possible?
蔡先生怎么可能啊
Students "Students
同学们「 同学们
classmates
同学们
Listen to me.
你们听我说
Cai Yuanpei asked us to resume classes.
蔡元培让我们复课
Said it was to protect those arrested classmates.
说是为了保护那些被捕的同学
But actually?
可实际呢
Look
你们看
Those arrested classmates
那些被捕的同学
Aren't you still being interrogated and sentenced?
不照样还是被审讯被判吗
This is obviously
这明显就是
He set a trap.
他下的一个圈套啊
We were all cheated by him.
咱们大家都被他给骗了
No way!
不可能吧
classmates
同学们
I can hear it.
我可听说了
This is Cao Rulin, but it costs a lot of money to hire a district.
这曹汝霖啊可是花重金雇区
To assassinate Cai Yuanpei and Peking University students
要刺杀蔡元培和北大学生
Xu Shuzheng has set up a cannon in Jingshan
徐树铮已在景山架起了大炮
To shell Peking University
要炮轰北大
Students, wake up.
同学们 醒醒吧
Don't let Cai Yuanpei fool you.
别让蔡元培给骗了
Ah, amazing!
了不起啊
The magazine effect run by Zhongfu has already appeared.
仲甫办的杂志社效应已经显现了
My vernacular novels have also worked.
我写的白话小说也见效了
The May 4th Movement swept away the tacky slavery of the people.
五四运动一扫国民的俗气奴气
Be petty.
和小家子气
Hold up the backbone of the Chinese people
撑起了中国人的脊梁
That's amazing.
太了不起了
yes
是啊
Yu just said it thoroughly.
豫才说得很透彻
After the May Fourth Student Parade
五四学生大游行以后
All of a sudden, over the years
一下子把多年来
All the contradictions have risen.
所有的矛盾捕升了
Patriotism or selling pressure
爱国还是卖压
Now it is in front of the Chinese people.
现在就是摆在中国人面前的
Daofenling
道分水岭
No one can get around where to go.
何去何从 谁也绕不过去
But according to my analysis
但是据我分析啊
The situation in these two days
这两天的形势
More subtle than the previous two days.
比前两天更加微妙了
Although it is said that the arrested students
虽然说被捕的学生
Was released.
被释放了
But the contradiction is more acute.
但是矛盾却更加尖锐了
Fu warlord
安福系军阀
Want to borrow the students to resume classes
想借着学生复课
And canceling the National Assembly.
和取消国民大会办两件事
The first one
第一件
sign a contract
签约
The second piece
第二件
Suppress the student movement
镇压学生运动
The reason why they are so thousands
他们之所以这么千
Just want to show
就是想显示
Ruling power over Chinese political power
对中国政权的统治力
So if you want to do these two things
那么想办成这两件事
The most critical
最为关键的
Is to subdue the leader of Peking University first.
就是要把北大的领头羊先制服
Who is the leader of Peking University?
北大领头羊是谁呀
Cai Yuanpei
蔡元培
Then this is the reactionaries.
那么这就是反动派
Now the primary target of attack
现在首要攻击的目标
Shouchang's analysis is very reasonable
守常分析得非常有道理
As far as I know
据我所知
The police department has issued a summons today.
今天警察厅已经发出了传票
To subpoena those people separately
要分别传讯那些
The arrested students who have been released.
已经释放了的被捕学生
Still claim to be investigated according to law
声称还是要依法追究
Their legal responsibility
他们的法律责任
in addition
另外
presidential palace
总统府
the State Council
国务院
Ministry of Education
教育部
Instructions have been issued.
都已经发出了训示
To reprimand Mr Cai Yuanpei for taking up his post.
要斥责蔡元培先生读职
I see and hear.
我是听说
The Anfu family has already defined Hu Renyuan.
安福系已经内定了胡仁源
Replace Mr Cai Yuanpei as the president of Peking University.
接替蔡元培先生做北大的校长
Mr Cai seems to be in a bad mood recently.
蔡先生最近好像心情不太好
I called him this morning.
今天早上我给他打电话
Want to see him?
想去看他
He was rejected.
被他拒绝了
Mr. Cai
蔡先生
寿昌兄
守常兄
beautiful
美
Please sit down.
你请坐
I came to see you.
我来看看您
You have something on your mind.
您是有心事
The police sent another summons.
警察厅又发来了传票
Arrested students
传讯被捕的学生
Trying to convict them.
想给他们定罪
Once these students are caught in the picture again
一旦这些学生再次身陷图唇
The possible consequences are unimaginable.
可能会出现的后果不堪设想
Are all young talents.
都是些青年 英才
full of youthful spirit
朝气蓬勃
Duan Qirui played a legal card.
段祺瑞这是打了一张法律牌
It is very deceptive.
具有很大的欺骗性
Mr. Cai
蔡先生
We have to make a good plan.
咱们得好好谋划一下才行
I've thought it over.
我已经考虑了再三
Didn't come up with a good intention either.
也没想出个好意出来
Sir, Chairman Wang Da is here.
先生 汪大委员长到
please
请
People!
子民呀
I've come to apologize to you.
我来向你请罪
Brother Botang, what are you doing?
伯棠兄 你这是什么
Now I'm a cat on hot bricks.
我现在已经是热锅上的蚂蚁
You're still joking with me.
你还跟我开这个玩笑
come
来
来唐波兄弟请坐吧
来伯棠兄 请坐吧
请坐寿昌兄
请坐守常兄
to be frank/honest with you
实不相瞒
Disreality
实不相满
Duan Qirui summoned me in the afternoon.
下午段祺瑞召见了我
Explicit diplomatic association
明令外交协会
May not interfere with the Paris Peace Conference signing.
不得干预巴黎和会签约
No domestic assembly shall be convened.
不得召集国内集会
Do not spread opinions different from those of the government.
不得散布与政府不同的意见
He also said
他还说
What 15,000 students in Beijing did.
北京学生一万五千人所为之事
The culprit is Peking University No.1 School.
祸首在北大一校
And the culprit of Peking University No.1 School
而北大一校的罪魁祸首
In the headmaster Cai Zimin
在校长蔡子民一身
Cai Min can no longer be the president of Peking University.
蔡子民断然不能再当北大校长
He has called Xu Shichang.
他已经给徐世昌打了电话
Propose Hu Renyuan to replace Cai Yuanpei.
提议胡仁源取代蔡元培
President of Peking University
任北大校长
Tian Huang replaced Fu Zengxiang as the education chief.
田应潢取代傅增湘任教育总长
In a few days, it will be submitted to the cabinet for agreement.
不日提请内阁议定
They don't have to bother.
不用他们劳神
I have submitted my resignation report three times.
我已经三次提交了辞呈报告
What matters now is
现在关键的是
Can't let the arrested students suffer again.
不能让被捕的学生再次蒙难
We can't let them go back to prison again.
不能让他们第二次再入监狱
People?
子民哪
I think about it.
我思前想后
If we take a long-term view.
要是从长计议的话
Is there any way to avoid this robbery?
有什么办法能够躲过这一劫
我说实话唐波兄弟
我说实话 伯棠兄
As long as I, the students of Peking University
只要我这些北大的学生们
Don't suffer again.
不要再次蒙难
As long as my Peking University is safe.
只要保证我北大平安
Let me Cai Yuanpei do what?
让我蔡元培干什么
I'll do whatever it takes.
我都在所不惜
The present situation
眼下这个情况
There's only one way.
只有一个办法
Thirty-Six Stratagems
三十六计
decamping being the best
走为上
leave
离开
Uncle Shen
申叔兄
I want to ask you a question.
想向你请教一个问题啊
You say
您说
You said it was going to rain, and Mom was going to get married.
你说这天要下雨娘要嫁人
Who is this mother talking about?
这个娘说的是谁呀
I thought.
我以为呀
The mother who wants to marry
要嫁的这个娘
She is by no means a child's mother
她绝不是孩子他娘
It should be an unmarried girl.
应该是未出阁的黄花大姑娘
Recently, I saw Wang Youguang's of Qing Dynasty.
最近我看了清人王有光的
Wu Xia Yan Lian
《吴下谚联》
It's going to rain and my mother is going to get married.
关于天要落雨娘要嫁人
This is how he explained it.
他是这么解释的
He said heaven.
他说天
Pure yang without yin
纯阳无阴
If it's going to rain, it's yang, but it's yin.
要下雨则阳之求阴也
Niang?
娘呢
It's solitary yin without yang.
是孤阴无阳
If you want to marry, you will seek yang from yin.
若要嫁人则阴之求阳也
If you go ahead, you will rot like a pulp.
如矢赴的 如浆点腐
This is what it is, this is what it is.
其理如是 其势如是
Look at this Wang Youguang
你看这王有光啊
He said this married mother.
他说的这个嫁人的娘
Is an unmarried woman.
是未婚的女子
If it's a married woman
如果是已婚的女子
It can't be secluded.
那就不可能是孤阴无阳
The so-called "when a man is married, a woman is married"
所谓的男大当婚 女大当嫁
My daughter is too old to stay.
女儿大了不中留
Stay, stay, stay, be enemies.
留来留去留成仇
It's humane that mother wants to get married.
就是娘要嫁人 这是人道
It's going to rain
天要下雨呢
It's heaven
是天道
Heaven and humanity are both irresistible.
天道人道这两者是不可抗逆的
Gu Sheng, please show us this.
辜汤生 您跟我们显摆这些
What do you mean?
是什么意思哪
I just want to tell you.
我就是想啊 告诉你们
If you want to go, it must go.
要走的它一定要走
What should be left will be left.
该留的它一定会留
This is independent of human will.
这是不以人的意志为转移的
Come and see!
快过来看
Why did Mr. Cai run away?
蔡先生怎么跑了
Doesn't he put oil on his feet?
他这不脚底抹油吗
He slipped away first.
他倒先溜了
Sir is here.
先生来了
Yes, sir.
先生好
I'm tired
我倦矣
Junma slayer goes by the way.
杀君马者道旁儿
People work hard to stop steam, but take a break.
民亦劳止 汽可小休
I want a little rest.
我欲小休矣
Peking University has officially resigned as principal.
北京大学校长之职已正式辞去
Assemble with other related schools.
其他向有关系之各学校各集会
Since May 9th
自五月九日起
Break away from everything.
一切脱离关系
Hereby declare
特此声明
Only those who know me forgive me.
惟知我者谅之
Three gentlemen, Mr. Cai left this note
三位先生 蔡先生留这个字条
What exactly does it mean?
到底是什么意思呀
Now there are all kinds of explanations.
现在有各种各样的解释
You are the authority.
您三位是权威
Tell us all about it.
给我们大家说说吧
Yes, sir. Tell us about it.
是啊先生 给我们讲讲吧
Are you a liberal arts student?
你是文科的学生吗
be
是
Can't you understand this?
这都看不懂吗
We can understand ourselves by living.
活我们能明自
We can understand everything.
话我们能明百
Words we can understand.
话我们能明白
But what about this truth?
但是这道理呢
classmates
同学们
Listen to me.
你们听我讲
Look
你们看
Mr. Cai
蔡先生
The beginning of this note
这个字条的开头
On the two allusions.
就上了两个典故
If we want to understand Mr Cai's mind
我们要想了解蔡先生的心思
We must first know these two allusions.
首先就要知道这两个典故
Look at this allusion.
你看 这一个典故是
Junma slayer goes by the way.
杀君马者道旁儿
It comes from what should be written in Han Dynasty.
它出自于汉代应所撰的
Common sense of custom
《风俗通义》
Its original text is
它的原文是
Long horse fat
长吏马肥
The watcher's swift move is also sudden.
观者快马之走骤也
Take advantage of his words.
乘者喜其言
Drive away endlessly
驱驰不已
As for Rui's death
至于睿死
As for death
至于死
Mr. Gu
辜先生
not get a thing out of
听不懂
You'd better tell us the vernacular.
您还是给我们讲白话吧
Yes, sir.
是啊先生
You'd better talk to us.
您还是给我们讲自话吧
Look at you, a liberal arts student
一看你这个文科的学生
It's just learning without being proficient.
就是学而不精啊
The meaning of this allusion is
这个典故的意思就是
There is an officer.
有一个官更
His horse is fattened and runs fast.
他的马养得很肥 跑得也很快
Be praised by passers-by
受到了路人的称赞
What about this rider?
这个骑马者呢
I began to gloat.
就开始扬扬得意
He is riding his horse and whipping his whip to keep running.
他是策马扬鞭 更奔跑不停
As a result, this horse was exhausted.
结果就把这个马给累死了
So Mr Cai quoted this allusion.
所以蔡先生引用这个典故
What exactly does it mean?
到底是啥意思呀
Don't worry.
你不要急
There is a second story.
这还有第二个典故
The people have been working hard enough
民亦劳止
Kexiaoxiu
汽可小休
It comes from The Book of Songs Daya.
它出自于 《诗经·大雅》
People's Labor
之《民劳》
Its second sentence begins with
它的第二句开始就是
The people have been working hard enough
民亦劳止
Kexiaoxiu
汽可小休
To caress the people of the king's capital
惠此中国
Think people
以为民
Tang Gong 'a
汤公啊
You can talk about it.
您这说来说去呀
Off topic.
说跑题了
Students mean to ask you.
人家学生的意思是问您
Mr. Cai, what does this note mean?
蔡先生这个字条到底为何意
The student
这位同学
Let me tell you.
我来告与你知
This killer of your horse is on the way.
这杀君马者道旁儿
This gentleman refers to the municipal government.
这个君指的是政府
This Maya
这个马呀
Refers to Cao Rulin and Zhang Zongxiang.
指的是曹汝霖和章宗祥
This roadside.
这个道旁儿
It's about you students.
说的便是你们这些学生
Cai Yuanpei means
蔡元培之意为
You students are in trouble.
你们这些学生闯了祸
He had to run away.
害得他不得不跑了
It can't be true
不会吧
Feiye
非也
This is for Master Cai.
你这是对蔡公的讼葳
classmates
同学们
I thought the monarch meant your classmates.
我以为君者指的就是你们同学们
Ma also refers to Master Cai himself.
马也指的就是蔡公他自己
As for the roadside.
至于道旁儿
That's the damn Paris peace treaty.
说的就是那该死的巴黎和约
And traitor Cao Zhanglu.
还有卖国贼曹章陆
The reason why Master Cai ran away
蔡公之所以出走
He was completely victimized by an adulterer.
他完全是被奸人所害
He did this.
他这样做
May be out of necessity.
可能是出于迫不得已
It may also be a delaying tactic.
也可能是缓兵之计
But I believe Gu Hongming.
但是我辜鸿铭相信
Master Cai will never abandon Peking University.
蔡公一定不会舍弃北大的
Good point!
说得好
It's going to rain and my mother is going to get married.
天要下雨 娘要嫁人
Suck It Up
随它去吧
Selling newspapers!Selling newspapers!
卖报卖报
Cai Yuanpei left school.
蔡元培离校出走
Leave a mysterious note
留下谜一样的纸条
Selling newspapers! Selling newspapers!
卖报 卖报
Sir, buy a newspaper.
先生买份报吧
Cai Yuanpei left school.
蔡元培离校出走
Left a mysterious note
留下了谜一样的纸条
Selling newspapers!Selling newspapers!
卖报卖报
The sacrifice was forced away by the government.
祭公是被政府逼走的
To save the students.
他为了救学生
I had to resign.
迫不得已辞了职
He can only turn to him if he goes through contradictions.
他走 矛盾才能转到他身上
Students can be rescued.
学生们才能获救
Fair enough. That's right.
说得对
The reason why Mr. Cai left without saying goodbye
蔡先生之所以不辞而别
One is to protect students.
一是为了保护学生
Second, so that we can't compromise
二是为了让我们不能妥协
Keep fighting.
继续抗争
The armed forces can seize the division.
三军可夺师也
Even an ordinary person has his unchangeable ambitions
匹夫不可夺志
Mr. Ji is not here.
祭先生不在
Just in time for all of us to let go
正好可以让我们大家放手
put into practice or action
付诸行动
I think our immediate priority.
我认为我们眼下的当务之急
When you want to carry out the Cai movement.
是要进行挽蔡运动
Not just Peking University.
不光是北大啊
It's the whole of Beijing
是整个北京
Even the whole of China.
乃至整个中国
Pinch the government with Mr. Cai
用蔡先生钳制住政府
In this way, the government can't take care of students.
这样政府就顾不上学生了
Let's discuss how to do it specifically.
我们还是商量一下具体怎么做吧
Yes, or please ask the Federation of Students to organize.
是不是还是请学联出面组织
It's not enough for the Federation of Students to come forward.
光是学联出面还不够
The direct target of the Cai movement is the government.
挽蔡运动的直接对象是政府
Then the teacher should take the lead.
那么教员就应该冲锋在前
I think we should get in touch right now.
我觉得我们现在应该马上联系
Chen Baoquan of Beijing Normal School
北京师范学校的陈宝泉
He took the lead.
由他出面牵头
And the organization was established.
组织并且成立
Beijing Federation of School Staff
北京各校教职员联合会
Negotiate with the government
出面跟政府交涉
Get ready at this time.
学联这个时候做好准备
Combine protest speeches and speeches.
把抗议 宣讲 演讲结合起来
Go deep into all levels of society.
深入到社会的各个层面
Let all China move.
让全中国都动起来
If you really can't, come to him for a general strike.
实在不行 就来他一个总罢课
I propose
我提议
By Peking University professor jointly to the Ministry of Education.
由北大教授联名给教育部
Write a statement.
写一个声明
Show that Peking University teachers and students
表明北大师生
Vow to advance and retreat with President Cai
誓与蔡校长共进退
Ask the Ministry of Education to retain Cai Yuanpei.
要求教育部挽留蔡元培
If Cai Yuanpei does not stay.
如蔡元培不留
Then all the professors of Peking University unanimously resigned.
则北大全体教授一致总辞职
If you have no objection.
大家没有什么异议的话
I volunteered to draft this statement.
我毛遂自荐 来起草这个声明
good
好
Then I'll get someone to sign it
那我找人签名
When I came here just now
刚才来的时候
I also met Gu Hongming and Liu Shipei.
我还碰到辜鸿铭和刘师培
They all specifically mentioned it to me.
他们都特别跟我提到
If there is any action.
说如果有什么行动的话
Be sure to inform them.
务必要通知到他们
We will certainly win the overwhelming support.
我们一定会争取到广大的支持的
Then everyone should do their job.
那大家就各司其职
Act now
马上行动
The president's office just called.
总长 总统府刚刚来电
Say Chen Baoquan Tanger and wait for eighteen people.
说陈宝泉 汤尔和等十八位
Principals of colleges and universities above secondary level in Beijing collectively wrote a letter.
北京中等以上高校校长集体上书
Suspend the Qing government to retain Cai Yuanpei
悬请政府挽留蔡元培
We are ordered to pay close attention.
责令我们一定要密切留意
Teachers in universities and colleges
各大高校教员情况
Petition of all professors of Peking University
北大全体教授请愿书
You will forward it to Prime Minister Qian immediately.
你马上转呈给钱总理
Those official documents on the desk
桌上的那些公文
Please also handle it together.
也请你们一并处理一下
I have to go now./I'm leaving now.
我要走了
The chief
总长这
This seat is not for people.
这个位置不是人坐的
I'm going to follow Cai Yuanpei's example and walk away.
我要效仿蔡元培一走了之
Don't look for me.
你们不要找我
You can't find me either.
你们也找不到我
Chief, you're gone.
总长您走了
What can we do about this mess?
这一摊子事可怎么办呢
It's going to rain and my mother is going to get married.
天要下雨 娘要嫁人
Suck It Up
随它去吧
cabinet minister
总长
Get you two here today.
今天把你们两位找来
Just want to discuss it.
就是想商量一下
The problems of the Ministry of Education and Peking University
教育部和北京大学的问题
It's been shaking for half a month.
晃半个月了
Student unrest is a wave of unrest.
学生闹事是一波未平一波又起呀
This makes me dizzy.
这搞得我晕头转向的
sit
坐
Cai Yuanpei ran away
蔡元培跑了
Make all the principals in Beijing resign.
弄得北京所有校长都跟着辞职了
It's a last resort
这不得已
I just issued a retention order.
我才下达了挽留令
I didn't expect this Fu Zengxiang.
没想到这个傅增湘
I also left without saying goodbye.
也来了个不辞而别
It has evaporated for several days.
蒸发好几天了
Now students are noisy in the street every day.
现在学生是天天在大街上闹啊
I heard it was returned.
怎么听说还还
People are dead.
还死了人了
Premier Qian, tell me about the situation.
钱总理你说说情况
A graduate of higher education in Tsinghua the day before yesterday.
前天 清华高等科的一个毕业生
Overworked and killed during the speech.
在演讲过程中 劳累过度痤死
A graduate of the former Jingshi University Hall yesterday.
昨天 原京师大学堂的一个毕业生
Throwing himself in Taiping Lake
在太平湖投湖自尽
Left a highly provocative suicide note.
留下了一份极具煽动性的遗书
Director Wu is worried that students will use this suicide note.
吴总监担心学生利用这份遗书
In the past two days, police forces have been deployed around the school.
近两日在学校周边加派了警力
Afraid of an accident
唯恐出事
This student thing can't be solved.
这学生的事情解决不了
You have no good days anywhere.
你们哪 都没有好日子了
Guys, tell me what to do.
两位说说吧 到底怎么办
You want me to say it?
要我说呀
The root is that we are too soft.
根子就是我们自己太软
Fu Zengxiang
傅增湘
He said that only appeasement can prevent an accident.
他说只有安抚才能不出事
Now it's appeasing the trouble.
现在安抚出乱子了
He ran away by himself.
他自己跑了
This kind of person can't accomplish enough, but can do more.
这种人成事不足败事有余
And Wu Bingxiang, an idiot.
还有吴炳湘这个蠢货
We have to release all the students we have caught.
硬要把抓来的学生都放了
Are you silly now?
现在傻了吧
These people who can read and write characters.
这些识文断字的人
Is to look at people's faces.
就是看人脸色办事
If you are soft, he will be hard.
你软他就硬
He is soft when you are hard.
你硬他就软
Premier Qian 1, what do you think?
钱总理1 你怎么看
I think the root of this matter is still in Paris.
我认为这件事的根本还在巴黎
The matter of the peace treaty is not resolved.
和约的事不解决
Students' affairs can't be solved
学生的事解决不了
One yard is one yard.
码是一码
What if we solve the students' problems first?
咱们先解决学生的问题怎么办
I have no choice.
我没有办法
I listen to the president.
我全听大总统的
President Qing's instructions
请大总统训示
Well, let me tell you something.
那好 那我就说说
I discussed it with Lao Duan recently.
最近我跟老段商量过了
The two of us have drawn up several articles.
我们俩拟出了几条
first
第一
Fu Zengxiang, chief of education, was relieved of his post as chief of staff.
免去教育总长傅增湘的总长职务
Tian Yinghuang replaced it.
由田应璜代之
Reject Cao Rulin Zhang Zongxiang
驳回曹汝霖 章宗祥
Lu Zongyu's resignation application
陆宗舆的辞职申请
Continue to reuse
继续重用
Thirdly, in view of Cai Yuanpei's resignation.
第三 鉴于蔡元培辞职不归
Hu Renyuan is in charge of Peking University temporarily.
由胡仁源暂时执掌北京大学
Fourth, instruct garrison headquarters to be reincarnated.
第四 责成京畿警备司令部
Step by step to command the Metropolitan Police Department.
步军统领 京师警察厅
Seriously protect the security of Beijing.
认真防护京城治安
Those who refuse to accept the pressure in case of correcting troubles.
遇有纠众滋事不服弹压者
Arrest and punish according to law
依法逮惩
fifth
第五
Trial the students who caused trouble on May 4th according to law.
依法审讯五月四滋事学生
Great president wise
大总统英明
Gentlemen, Master Ge, here they come.
先生们 葛师傅他们来了
Mr. Chen
陈先生
sir
先生
We represent thousands of workers in Changxindian.
我们代表长辛店的几千工友
To mourn the martyrs who died for their country.
来悼念为国捐躯的烈士
When I came
我来的时候
The workmates asked me to give you a message.
工友们托我给您带话
We must not let the current asshole government
绝不能让现在的浑蛋政府
Lost Qingdao.
把青岛给丢了
If Xu Shichang dares to betray his country
如果徐世昌胆敢卖国
Our workers resolutely refuse to agree.
我们工人坚决不答应
thank you
谢谢
Sir, this is the decision just made by the Federation of Students.
先生 这是学联刚刚下的决议
Please sit down for a while.
您先坐一会儿
Be busy first.
您先忙
Who have you been to Qingdao
你们谁去过青岛啊
Is Qingdao beautiful?
青岛美吗
I've never been there once.
我一次都没去过
Xingang promised me that
心刚答应我说
After graduation
毕业之后
Take me back to my hometown in Qingdao.
就带我回青岛老家
Marry me?
跟我结婚呢
He also told me
他还跟我讲
Said there was a trestle in Qingdao.
说青岛有一个栈桥
It's just a long, long bridge
就是一个很长很长的桥
It's over a hundred meters.
有一百多米呢
All the way to the sea.
一直通到海里边
He said to go to the end of the bridge.
他说走到桥的尽头
You can see a white lighthouse.
能看到一个白色的灯塔
Especially nice.
特别好看
Xingang also laughed at me and said
心刚还笑话我说
I am a girl.
我一个女孩子
I dare not walk on the trestle by myself.
肯定不敢自己走上栈桥的
Because sometimes the wind is very strong and the waves are very big.
因为有时候风很大浪很大
A wave came and hit me into the sea.
一个浪过来就把我打到海里了
新港还说
心刚还说
If I fall into the water
如果我掉到水里了
He certainly won't save me.
他肯定不会救我的
He stood on the trestle and laughed.
他就站在栈桥上笑
I choke on water.
看我呛水
Let me learn to swim by myself.
他让我自己已学会游泳
Jenny, why is he so bad?
师母您说他怎么这么坏呀
done
好了
Good boy
好孩子
stop crying
别哭了
alright
好了好了
Good boy
好孩子
Stop crying.
不哭了
白兰跟刘梅一起
白兰 跟柳眉一起
Move to the house.
搬到家里来住
Go to France to work and study together.
一块去法国勤工俭学
You're gone.
君去矣
Bring blood to Qingdao.
甘将热血红青岛
come
来
Wulaiye
吾来也
No wild slaves can shake Mount Tai.
不许狂奴撼泰山
mount
挂上
Saving the nation and learning
救国与做学问
Ripe, light, big and small.
熟重熟轻熟大熟小
be self-evident
不辩自明
Is inseparable from the fate of the individual and the country.
个人和国家的命运是分不开的
Now I understand this movement.
我现在体会这场运动
In addition to letting the people act directly
除了让人民直接行动
Beyond directly solving the problem
直接解决问题之外
Add two more words.
还要再加两个字
No impossible victory.
没有 不可能胜利
Teachers and students.
各位老师 各位同学
Guo Xingang loves this country.
郭心刚因为爱这个国家
Gave his precious life.
献出了他宝贵的生命
He is our Peking University.
他是我们北京大学
Beijing academic circles
北京学界
Even the glory and pride of the whole of China.
乃至全中国的光荣和骄傲
We will never forget him.
我们永远不会忘记他
We're going to use Guo Xingang's death
我们要用郭心刚的死
Awaken the people
唤醒民众
Inherit its ambition
继承其志
Complete its unfinished business
完成其未竟之事业
So we decided
所以我们决定
Here on the afternoon of May 18th.
五月十八号下午在这儿
Hold a memorial meeting for Guo Xingang martyrs.
举行郭心刚烈士的追悼大会
Meanwhile, I declare
同时我宣布
Schools above secondary school in Beijing
北京中等以上学校
students'federation
学生联合会
Beijing School Staff Federation
北京各校教职员工联合会
Resolution of the meeting
会议的决议
In order to resist the perverse actions of Beiyang government
为了抵制北洋政府的倒行逆施
It is decided that from May 19th
决定 自五月十九号起
All schools in Beijing
北京各校全体
General strike
总罢课
This is left by Xingang's blood.
这是心刚的血留下的
Let's observe silence for Xingang.
让我们一起为心刚默哀
Strike and protest and preach to mobilize the masses.
罢课要和抗议宣讲发动群众
band together
结合起来
Civilian education lecture group
平民教育讲演团
To play a greater role.
要发挥更大的作用
You have to make a plan.
你们要做好计划
Not only should we go deep into all classes in Beijing.
不光要深入到北京的各个阶层
Even deeper.
还要深入到
Shanghai, Jinan and Changsha
上海南京 济南 长沙
These big cities
这些大的城市
Win the support of the whole country
争取全国的支持
And in these big cities
并且要在这些大的城市
Also hold Guo Xingang's memorial service
也开郭心刚的追悼会
This is the best way to mobilize the masses.
这是发动群众最好的方式
I'm going to Changsha in a few days.
我准备过几天去一趟长沙
I heard Mao Zedong and them are over there.
听说毛泽东他们在那边
Make a splash.
搞得风生水起的
I'm going to learn from them.
我要去向他们取取经
Make a horizontal alliance.
搞一下横向联合
Especially Shanghai.
特别是上海
That is the gathering place of the working class.
那是工人阶级的聚集地
Let Shanghai become a student movement
要让上海成为学生运动的
The second center
第二个中心
Even play a greater role.
甚至发挥更大的作用
I went to Shanghai to preach Guo Xingang.
我去上海宣讲郭心刚
good
好
Then we'll prepare more propaganda groups for the south.
那我们就多准备几个南下宣讲团
Yannian Qiaonian
延年 乔年
I'm going to take a job with you.
我要抓你们一个差
I just wrote an article.
我刚刚写了一篇文章
The title is
题目是
"Inform all sides about the Shandong issue"
《为山东问题敬告各方面》
This article is written for the general strike tomorrow.
这篇文章是为了明天总罢课写的
Mainly want to tell you honestly.
主要是想告诚大家
Don't think that the Shandong problem
千万不要以为山东问题
It's just a matter of the survival of a province.
仅仅是一个省的存亡问题
It's not just a matter of academic circles.
也不光是学界一家的事情
But the whole of China.
而是全中国的事情